Guide to the Dr. Edison E. Oberholtzer Papers
University of Houston Libraries
Dr. Edison E. Oberholtzer Papers
1905-1967
1999-010
Oberholtzer, E. E. (Edison Ellsworth), 1880-1954
5.00 Linear Feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
The papers of Edison Ellsworth Oberholtzer contain employment contracts, information relating to the University of Houston, photographs, newspapers, certificates, and diplomas.
Biographical Information:
Edison Ellsworth Oberholtzer began his career as a school teacher in rural Indiana. He served as Superintendent of Tulsa public schools from 1913 to 1923 and Superintendent of the Houston Independent School District from 1924 to 1927. With the formation of the Houston Junior College in 1927, Oberholtzer was named president. Oberholtzer remained president through the change from a two-year to a four-year institution in 1934. In 1945 Senate Bill (SB) 207 passed and gave the authority to the Board of Education of HISD to divorce the management of the University of Houston from the public schools. E.E. Oberholtzer was named as president and continued in that capacity until his retirement in 1950.
Oberholtzer received his bachelor and master degrees from the University of Chicago and his doctorate from Columbia University in 1934.
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Corporate Name:
University of Houston
Personal Name:
Oberholtzer, E. E. (Edison Ellsworth), 1880-1954
Conditions Governing Access:
Requests for permission to publish material from the collection should be discussed with the University Archivist
Acquisition Information
Information of acquisition method not available.
Scope and Contents
The papers of Edison Ellsworth Oberholtzer contain employment contracts, information relating to the University of Houston, photographs, newspapers, certificates, and diplomas. Dr. Oberholtzer's papers are arranged in five series. The collection contains material dating from 1905 to 1967. A few of the photographs may precede 1905. Most of the material was obtained from Richard A. Walker in January 2003. Mr. Walker is a Professor of Geography at the University of California, Berkeley and a grand nephew of Dr. Oberholtzer.
Detailed List of Contents
- Employment Contracts, 1911-1950
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of four folders containing the employment contracts for E.E. Oberholtzer, dating from 1911 to 1950 and arranged chronologically.
  - Clinton, Indiana, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Tulsa, Oklahoma, 1914-1920 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - HISD, 1924-1938 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - University of Houston, 1945-1950 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- University of Houston, 1938-1955
  This series consists of twenty-one folders, probably office files, relating to various aspects of the University of Houston.
  - Achievements and Services Related to the War Effort, University of Houston, 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Alphabetical List of Contributors (Confidential), 1938 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Convocation-Thirteenth Annual, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Ezekiel W. Cullen Building, The (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Growth and Development of the University of Houston, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - History of the University of Houston, 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Inaugural Address of Acceptance of Dr. E.E. Oberholtzer, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Junior College Appropriation Bill, 1945-1947 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - M.D. Anderson Memorial Library, The (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Minutes of the Board of Education of HISD (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Notes: Library Appreciation Speech (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Oberholtzer, E.E., President Emeritus, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Painting Presentation of E.E. Oberholtzer, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Pamphlets, 1950-1951 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Policies and Objectives of the University of Houston, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Quotations (Probably used in speeches) (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Resolution Creating an Advisory Board for the University of Houston, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Senate Bill No. 207 (Bill separating the University of Houston), 1945 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Summary of the Organization and Program of the University of Houston (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - University of Houston, Symphony, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - University of Houston, The, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Personal
  This series consists of seven folders relating to personal aspects of the Oberholtzer family. The materials date from 1910 to 1959 and are arranged alphabetically.
  - Acknowledgements-Deaths of Mr. and Mrs. Oberholtzer, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Birth and Death Certificates and Will of Mr and Mrs. Oberholtzer, 1937-1954 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence, 1954-1967 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Death Announcements of E.E. Oberholtzer, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Life Insurance and Mortgage, 1922-1935 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Personal Correspondence and Notes, 1910-1959 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Tribute Cards, E.E. Oberholtzer (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Miscellaneous
  This series contains four folders of miscellaneous materials dating between 1924 and 1967 and arranged chronologically.
  - Houston High Schools Teachers Handbook, 1924-1925 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - School Management Magazine, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - The Teachers College Journal, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Tenth Annual Community Recognition, Dinner, Denver, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Photographs
  This series contains four folders containing family photographs spanning the life of E.E.Oberholtzer.
  - Photographs (Box 1, Folder 37-40)
  - Photographs K.E. Oberholtzer (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Photographs (Box 2, Item 1)
  - Tin Plate (Box 2, Item 2)
  - Photographs, Identified and Unidentified (Box 2, Item 3)
  - Black and White Cased Image (3) (Box 2, Item 4)
  - Panoramic Photograph (Box 3, Item 1)
  - Miscellaneous Photographs (Box 4, Item 1)
- Diplomas and Certificates
  This series contains fourteen diplomas or certificates awarded to the Oberholtzers that date between 1904 and 1959 and are arranged chronologically.
  - Indiana Teachers' Reading Circle, 1904 (Box 5, Item 1)
  - State of Indiana Teacher's State Certificate, 1905 (Box 5, Item 2)
  - State of Indiana Teacher's Professional Certificate, 1908 (Box 5, Item 3)
  - Indiana State Normal School, Course of Instruction, 1909 (Box 5, Item 4)
  - The University of Chicago, Germanic Languages, 1909 (Box 5, Item 5)
  - Universitas Chicaginienis, Baccalaurei in Philosophia, 1910 (Box 5, Item 6)
  - Lincoln-Jefferson University, Bachelor of Law, 1912 (Box 5, Item 7)
  - Sabine Royalty Corporation, 1940 (Box 5, Item 8)
  - Rotary Club of Houston, Membership, 1950 (Box 5, Item 9)
  - American Association of School, 1952 (Box 5, Item 10)
  - Diploma, Honorary degree from the University of Houston, 1950 (Box 5, Item 11)
  - Book of Remembrance, 1954 (Box 5, Item 12)
  - Tribute to Myrtle May Barr Oberholtzer, 1959 (Box 5, Item 13)
  - Diploma Certificate (in exhibit) (Box 5, Item 14)
- Newspapers
  This series contains five newspapers arranged chronologically.
  - The Houston Post-Dispatch, 1929 (Box 5, Item 15)
  - The Cougar, 1945 (Box 5, Item 16)
  - The Cougar, 1949 (Box 5, Item 17)
  - The Extra, 1955 (Box 5, Item 18)
  - The Tulsa World, (single page), 1964 (Box 5, Item 19)